Guide to the Albert Van Helden academic papers, 1976-1989 MS 443
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Albert Van Helden academic papers
1976-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
van Helden, Albert, 1940-
MS 443
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
This collection consists of astronomer Albert Van Helden's academic papers and encompass his work with various professional organizations, as well as with Rice University related committees and projects.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Van Helden was born on March 7, 1940 in the The Hague, Netherlands, came to the United States in 1955, and later became a naturalized citizen. He received a B.S. in Engineering degree from Stevens Institute of Technology in 1962, Master of Science from Stevens in 1964, Master of Arts in History from University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, in 1967, and a doctorate from the University of London, Imperial College in the History of Science in 1970. Dr. Van Helden came to Rice University as an Assistant Professor of History in 1970, was promoted to full professor in 1983, and served as Chairman of the Department of History in 1987. In addition to his teaching duties at Rice in the field of history of science, Dr. Van Helden has published extensively on the history of astronomy, and on the invention and development of the telescope. He is closely associated with the Galileo Project at Rice University that examines the history, art, and culture of Galileo and of science in 17th century Italy.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of astronomer Albert Van Helden's academic papers and encompass his work with various professional organizations, as well as with Rice University related committees and projects.
Access Restrictions
The bulk of this material is open for research; however, some files are restricted as noted.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Professor Albert Van Helden, June 1990.
Index Terms
Subjects
Astronomy; Universities and colleges
- Series I: Non-Rice University committees and projects, 246892
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1987-89, 246911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1976-77, 246910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Center for the History of Leadership Institutions, 1984-85, 246909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Day the Universe Changed," 1985-86, 246908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1976, 246907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hermann Hospital history proposal, 1981, 246906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History of Science society, 1985-1986, 246905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Human Values and Health proposed UT program, 1980, 246904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Institute on Human Values in Medicine, 1975-1976, 246903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Johnson Space Center Archives, 1978-81, 246902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mellon Foundation, 1979, 1989, 246901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - National Air and Space Museum, 1987, 246900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1970s, 246899 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Science Foundation proposal review, 1982, 246898 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oxford International Conference on Archaeoastronomy, 1986, 246897 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - South Central Society for 18th Century Studies, 1976, 246896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Southwestern Social Science Association, 1972-73, 246895 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Telescope in the 17th Century, 1971, 246894 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "When are Competent Patients Incompetent?," 1984, 246893 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: Rice University committees and projects, 246866
  - Animal Welfare Committee, 1984, 246891 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Baker College Associate materials, 1978/79, 246890 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barkus Collection, 1979, 246889 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Club Sports Program, 1980, 246888 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Rice Ad-Hoc] Committee on Committees, 1985, 246887 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rice Committees, miscellaneous, 246886 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Course Proposals, 1975, 1983, 246885 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dean of Humanities Search, 1980 [Restricted], 246884 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Faculty Convocation, 1985, 246883 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Graduate student evaluations/recommendations, 1979-1984 [Restricted], 246882 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Committee on International Education, 1986-87, 246881 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Medieval Studies, 1984-87, 246880 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Presidential Search Committee, 1985 [Restricted], 246879 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Promotion materials, 1982/1983 [Restricted], 246878 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Research and travel grants, 246877 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Science program ad-hoc committee, 1977, 246876 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Scientia, 1982-83, 246875 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Scientia, 1984-85, 246874 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Scientia 1985-87, 246873 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Scientific Revolution lectures, 1971,1978, 246872 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Self-study panel on Athletics, 1983-84, 246871 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Self-study Steering Committee, 1985, 246870 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Self-study sub-panel on Intramurals/Club sports, 1983-84, 246869 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Tenure and Promotion Ad-Hoc Committee, 1985 [Restricted], 246868 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - University Fund Council, 1989-90 [Restricted], 246867 (Box 1, Folder 44)